Guide to the John H. Wright U.S. Civil War and related ephemera collection, 1838-1936 MS 061
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
John H. Wright U.S. Civil War and related ephemera collection
1838-1936
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Wright, John
MS 061
10 Linear Feet (17 boxes)
U.S. Civil war imprints and currency, various 19th century broadsides, brief histories of Army Generals including U.S. Grant, W.T. Sherman, A.E.Burnside, and others, as well as other ephemera such as Mussolini's shaving kit. This material was collected over a period of years by John H. Wright.
Historical Sketch
John H. Wright (1906-1990) attended Central High School in Houston and was a 1928 Rice graduate. He worked for Star Engraving Company and Taylor Publishing Company. He was married to Ruby Gow (d. 1986) and was an avid collector of Confederate printed materials. His passion for collecting resulted in the publishing of "Compendium," a bibliography of printed Confederacy items.
Scope and Contents
U.S. Civil war imprints and currency, various 19th century broadsides, brief histories of Army Generals including U.S. Grant, W.T. Sherman, A.E.Burnside, and others, as well as other ephemera such as Benito Mussolini's personalized Gilette shaving kit. This material was collected over a period of years by John H. Wright.
Books donated by Mr. Wright have been cataloged separately.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Stored onsite in the vault at the Woodson Research Center.
Acquisition Information
This material was donated by John H. Wright over a period of 30 years, circa 1960-1990.
Index Terms
Subjects
War; American Civil War (United States: 1861-1865)
Document Types
photographs; money; pamphlets; broadsides (notices); documents
Places
United States
Subjects (Persons)
Mussolini, Benito, 1883-1945; Wright, John
- Series I: Currency, broadsides and ephemera, 246353
  - Confederate currency: $1 bill (1), 246411 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Confederate currency: $5 bill (75), 246410 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Confederate currency: $10 bill (210), 246409 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Confederate currency: $20 bill (119), 246408 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Confederate currency: $50 bill (2), 246407 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Confederate currency: $100 bill (19), 246406 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Southern currency: 29 bills, 246405 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Texas currency: 10 bills, 246404 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - $2 bill and listing of coins, 246403 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Coins, 246402 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Benito Mussolini shaving kit documentation; Benito Mussolini shaving kit: Gillette safety razor in leather case with initials "BM" under wreath on outside; gold plated pieces include 1 razor, 2 talc shakers, 1 razor blade holder; all have initials "BM", 246401 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - R.G. Carter correspondence, 1935-36, 246400 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Broadside: "An Address to the Republicans of Portage County [Ohio]," Oct. 3, 1881, 246399 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Joseph Pennell memorial, 246398 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Broadside: Jacob Horne report, May 24, 1838, 246397 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Broadside: "Texian", 246396 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Broadside: "Address: Our Heroes, the Leaders of a New Reformation", 246395 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Broadside and pamphlet in German, 246394 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Autograph book: "Photographs and Autographs of the Present County Officers-Elect of Otsego County, New York," 1860, 246393 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Histories of Poor Boys who have become rich, and Other Famous People" [originally packaged in Duke's cigarettes]: Ole Bull; Jas. G. Blaine; Robt. Ingersoll; Josef Hoffman, 246392 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Histories of Poor Boys who have become rich, and Other Famous People [originally packaged in Duke's cigarettes]: Ole Bull; Jas. G. Blaine; Robt. Ingersoll; Josef Hoffman, 246391 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Subseries A: Histories of the Following Generals. Series of Small Books, 1888 [originally packaged in Duke's cigarettes]:, 246372 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - N.P. Banks, 246390
    - D.C. Buell, 246389
    - A.E. Burnside, 246388
    - Adml. Farragut, 246387
    - A.H. Foote, 246386
    - Gen. Garfield, 246385
    - Genl. Gilmore, 246384
    - Gen. U.S. Grant, 246383
    - Gen. H.W. Halleck, 246382
    - Gen. McClellan, 246381
    - Genl. J. McDowell, 246380
    - Gen. G. Meade, 246379
    - W.S. Rosencrans, 246378
    - Gen. Winfield Scott, 246377
    - Gen. Phil. Sheridan, 246376
    - Gen. W.T. Sherman, 246375
    - Gen. F. Sigel, 246374
    - Pages from The Little Primer, 1829, 246373
  - Yonkers Military Institute invitation, 246371 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - The Sun advertising bill (2), 246370 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Confederate bonds, 246369 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Broadside: "Proclamation to the People of Texas", 246368 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Broadside: "Proclamation by the Governor of the State of Texas", 246367 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Selections from the Bouts-Rimes of John Tenniel, 246366 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Album of reproductions of Confederate currency, 246365 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Album of reproductions of Confederate currency, 246364 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - The Picture Story of the Port Hudson Battlefield, 1863 and other Louisiana Civil War Scenes, 246363 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Map of Atlanta as of 1938, 246362 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - The Photographic History of the Civil War advertising pages, 246361 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - The Soldier in Our Civil War, incomplete pages, 246360 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - The Soldier in Our Civil War, Part 12, 246359 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - The Soldier in Our Civil War, Part 13, 246358 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - The Soldier in Our Civil War, Part 14, 246357 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - The Soldier in Our Civil War, Part 15, 246356 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Framed $50 Confederate bill, 246355 (Box 2, Folder -)
  - Framed Republic of Texas invoice, 246354 (Box 2, Folder -)
- Series II: Imprints, booklets and brochures, 246340
  - Confederacy, 246352 (Box 3-4, Folder -)
  - Lectures/addresses, 246351 (Box 5, Folder -)
  - Personalities: Davis, Lee, Lincoln, Jackson, 246350 (Box 6, Folder -)
  - Personalities, general, 246349 (Box 7, Folder -)
  - Georgia, 246348 (Box 8, Folder -)
  - Louisiana, Mississippi, 246347 (Box 9, Folder -)
  - Virginia, 246346 (Box 10-11, Folder -)
  - Tennessee, Kentucky, 246345 (Box 12, Folder -)
  - Alabama, Missouri, New York, Maryland, 246344 (Box 13, Folder -)
  - North Carolina, South Carolina, South, 246343 (Box 14-15, Folder -)
  - Florida, Arkansas, Oklahoma, Indiana, Vermont, Kansas, Ohio, 246342 (Box 16, Folder -)
  - Texas, Pennsylvania, 246341 (Box 17, Folder -)